{"tossups": [{"question": "<b><u>Members of the \u201cCamerata\u201d from what is today this country included the</u></b> <b><u>composer of the opera</u> </b><em><b><u>Dafne</u></b></em><b><u>. Another composer from this modern country wrote in a</u></b> <b><u>highly chromatic style after murdering his wife and her lover. A girls\u2019 orphanage (*)</u></b> <b>in this modern country is where a man nicknamed the \u201cRed Priest\u201d worked when composing </b><em><b>The Contest Between Harmony and Invention</b></em><b>. In 1607, a composer from what is now this country composed the earliest opera that is still regularly performed, (*) </b><em>L\u2019Orfeo</em>. For the point, name this home country of the composers Vivaldi and Monteverdi.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Italy</u></b> (or <b><u>Italian</u></b> Republic; or Repubblica <b><u>Italia</u></b>na; the first two composers are Jacopo Peri and Carlo Gesualdo)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>In a poem partly titled for this group, a member claims \u201cFor we're all of us</u></b> <b><u>nigh to the workhouse.\u201d A member of this group states \u201cwe were heroes once, sir.</u></b> <b><u>Please, write we are starving now\" in a work titled for the \u201cLast\u201d of them by Rudyard</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> Kipling. Another work notes how they faced \u201ccannon to right\u201d and \u201ccannon to left\u201d as \u201cthey rode\u2026 well.\u201d That work about 600 members of this group who (*) </b>rode \u201cinto the jaws of Death\u201d focused on their actions during the Crimean War. For the point, name this British cavalry force whose \u201cCharge\" was immortalized by Tennyson.", "answer": "<b><u>Light Brigade</u></b> (accept \"Last of the <b><u>Light Brigade</u></b>; accept \"Charge of the <b><u>Light</u></b> <b><u>Brigade</u></b>\")", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "<b><u>The Restoration Movement began during this larger historical period as an</u></b> <b><u>ideology which aimed to remove all the denominational labels from Christianity and</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> uniting the church. This period influence in western New York led to that region being dubbed the (*) </b>\"Burned-Over District\". For the point, name this 19th century period of religious revivalism in the U.S. which saw the growth of Methodism and the Baptists, along with the birth of Mormonism and Adventism.", "answer": "<b><u>Second Great Awakening</u></b> (prompt on partial answers; do not accept or prompt on \"First Great Awakening\")", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b><u>This scientist claimed to have once dissected a dolphin in the Grecian Coffee</u></b> <b><u>House with Edmund Halley and Hans Sloane. This man, who served as the twelfth</u></b> <b><u>president of the Royal Society, co-names a (+)</u> root-finding method with Joseph Raphson. This eccentric scientist, who developed a complex Biblical chronology, is best known for developing the three (*) </b>fundamental laws of his namesake type of physics. For the point, name this British physicist who allegedly discovered the principle of gravity after an apple fell on his head.", "answer": "Isaac <b><u>Newton</u></b> (or Sir Isaac <b><u>Newton</u></b>)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Misc Science"}, {"question": "<b><u>One businessman from this state provided an advance of 3000 pounds for the</u></b> <b><u>American portion of the Great Exhibition in London. That man, who may be better</u></b> <b><u>known for working with the father of J.P. Morgan as partners in the banking business,</u></b> <b><u>was George (+)</u> Peabody. An abolitionist from this state accumulated a large fortune in the railroad business, and left much of it to founding an institution that includes the (*) </b>Bloomberg School of Public Health. For the point, name this state where Johns Hopkins University was founded in Baltimore.", "answer": "<b><u>Maryland</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>John Waller wrote about the \u201cExtraordinary Story\u201d of an event characterized</u></b> <b><u>by the mass occurrence of this action, which may have been started by a woman</u></b> <b><u>named Frau Troffea. Athanasius Kircher came up with a remedy involving this action</u></b> <b><u>to cure individuals like a woman from (+)</u> Apulia who had been bitten by a tarantula. A 1518 plague was characterized by the mass occurrence of this action, which occurred in frenzies during (*) </b>choreomania [[\"CORE\"-ee-oh-\"mania\"]]. For the point, name this activity that names a \"mania\" in which participants moved to music.", "answer": "<b><u>Dancing</u></b> (accept <b><u>Tarantism</u></b>; accept <b><u>Tarantella</u></b>; accept <b><u>Chorea</u></b> or <b><u>Choreo</u></b>mania before \u201cchoreomania\u201d is mentioned; accept <b><u>Dancing</u></b> plague; do not accept or prompt on \u201cplaying music\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>An emissary named Goldenshoes helped end a war on this island, which</u></b> <b><u>suffered from Murat Reis's Turkish Abductions, a series of slave raids by North</u></b> <b><u>African pirates. This island was unified with another country by the Old (+)</u> Covenant. This island faced internal strife in the Age of the Sturlungs, and its population suffered from fluoride poisoning in the Mist Hardships. The (*) </b>Althing governs this island, which is featured in the sagas of Snorri Sturluson. For the point, name this Nordic island country, once inhabited by Vikings.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Iceland</u></b> (or Lydveldid <b><u>\u00cdsland</u></b> [[EEST-lahnt]])", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The government of Mexico attempted to remove independent</u> </b><em><b><u>ambulantes</u></b></em><b><u> in</u></b> <b><u>an effort to support small</u> </b><em><b><u>tianguis</u></b></em><b><u> [[tee-AHN-gweess]], a variety of this locale, which</u></b> <b><u>dates back to the Aztec. It's not a Forum or Temple, but (+)</u> Apollodorus of Damascus built one of these places named for Trajan on the edge of Quirinal Hill, which was expanded in medieval times by adding floor levels and defensive batteries. The (*) </b>Mercato Nuovo of Florence is an example of, for the point, what type of locale where food, livestock and other items are sold?", "answer": "<b><u>Market</u></b>places (accept <b><u>Bazaar</u></b>; prompt on \"store\")", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>A writing system from this civilization contained the Quartier Mu inscription</u></b> <b><u>and the Petras deposit inscriptions. Luigi Pernier discovered this civilization's (+)</u></b> <b>Phaistos fired clay disc. A legendary labyrinth holding a half bull half man is associated with this civilization. Arthur (*) </b>Evans discovered this civilization's Linear A script and its most famous site is Knossos palace. For the point, name this Bronze Age civilization based out of Crete.", "answer": "<b><u>Minoan</u></b> Civilization (accept <b><u>Minoan</u></b>s; prompt on \"Cretans\")", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In her teen years, this woman took music lessons from Henry Mannox with</u></b> <b><u>whom she also had a relationship before meeting her husband who called her the</u></b> <b><u>\"very jewel of womanhood.\" After her marriage in England, this woman had an affair</u></b> <b><u>with her distant cousin, Thomas (+)</u> Culpeper. Upon her husband\u2019s discovery of this and after the executions of Culpeper and Francis Dereham, this woman was decapitated with one blow of an executioner\u2019s axe in the (*) </b>Tower of London. For the point, name this fifth wife of Henry VIII, the second to be beheaded.", "answer": "Catherine <b><u>Howard</u></b> (prompt on \"Catherine\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This leader said \"the man who does not write for his entire people is not a</u></b> <b><u>poet\" in a speech supporting his July Theses, a reverse of previous liberalization</u></b> <b><u>efforts. This man forced scientists to put his illiterate wife, (+)</u> Elena, in the credits of research papers, and later, a firing squad executed both on public Television. This man, who used the Securitate secret police, was the only leader subjected to a (*) </b>violent overthrow during the anti-Communist Revolutions of 1989. For the point, name this Romanian dictator during the Cold War.", "answer": "Nicolae <b><u>Ceau\u0219escu</u></b> [[chow-CHESS-koo]]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 2010, historian Tom Buk-Swienty revealed that a former king of this</u></b> <b><u>country secretly negotiated to become part of the confederation of a southern</u></b> <b><u>neighbor, though that move was rejected. The Treaty of Vienna resulted in this</u></b> <b><u>country ceding several territories, including Saxe-Lauenburg, to (+)</u> Prussia and Austria, who fought a war the next year over another ceded region, Schleswig-Holstein. During World War Two, this country's ruler symbolically (*) </b>rode a horse through its capital every day while occupied by Nazi Germany. For the point, name this country, once ruled by Christian X [[the tenth]] from Copenhagen.", "answer": "<b><u>Denmark</u></b> (or <b><u>Danmark</u></b>; accept Kingdom of <b><u>Denmark</u></b>; or Kongeriget <b><u>Danmark</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>During one of these events, Mayor Abe Beame noted that \"we've seen our</u></b> <b><u>citizens subjected to violence, vandalism, theft, and discomfort\" after 75 stores were</u></b> <b><u>looted in Crown Heights. DJ Grandmaster Caz partially attributed the rise of (+)</u> hip-hop to one of these events in New York City in 1977. A software bug in an Ohio-based company led to a massive 2003 event of this type across the Northeast. Thousands of people were stranded on the (*) </b>subway system during, for the point, what kind of event, a 1965 example of which inspired the film <em>Where Were You When the Lights Went Out?</em>", "answer": "<b><u>Blackout</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Power outage</u></b>; accept clear knowledge equivalents such as <b><u>Loss of electricity</u></b> or <b><u>Power outage</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this city, Governor William Pitt Kellogg was turned out by the White League</u></b> <b><u>in the Battle of Liberty Place. A mixed-race man from this city deliberately broke the</u></b> <b><u>Separate (*)</u> Car Act by boarding a \"whites only\" train car, leading to the case </b><em><b>Plessy v. </b><b>Ferguson</b></em><b>. George W. Bush told (*) </b>FEMA director Michael Brown \"you're doing a heck of a job\" following a disaster in this city that impacted areas like the French Quarter. For the point, name this city that suffered massive damage following Hurricane Katrina.", "answer": "<b><u>New Orleans</u></b> (accept La <b><u>Nouvelle-Orl\u00e9ans</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>With Prime Minister Katsura Taro, this man names an agreement which</u></b> <b><u>established</u> </b><em><b><u>de jure</u></b></em><b><u> Japanese hegemony over Korea and protection of U.S. control of</u></b> <b><u>Philippines. As (*)</u> Chief Justice, this politician oversaw the case </b><em><b>McGrain v. Daugherty </b></em><b>which persecuted those involved in the Teapot Dome Scandal. With Philander Knox, this President established the policy of (*) </b>\"Dollar Diplomacy\" with Latin America, while this incumbent only won two states after splitting votes with his former mentor, Theodore Roosevelt. For the point, name this victor of the Election of 1908, a Republican politician from Ohio.", "answer": "William Howard <b><u>Taft</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A woman with this surname was called \"the female Beecher of the rostrum\"</u></b> <b><u>for her role as minister at a church in Racine, Wisconsin. That woman helped found</u></b> <b><u>the New England Suffrage Association and was named Olympia. The death of Elijah</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> Lovejoy prompted a man of this surname to state, \u201cI consecrate my life to the destruction of slavery.\" That man was the namesake of a song whose tune was adapted into the (*) </b>\u201cBattle Hymn of the Republic.\u201d For the point, give this surname of John, who led the raid on Harper\u2019s Ferry.", "answer": "<b><u>Brown</u></b> (accept John <b><u>Brown</u></b>; accept Olympia <b><u>Brown</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A leader of this country created the \"National Reconstruction,\" including</u></b> <b><u>Operation Keep Right to encourage driving on the right as well as Operation Feed</u></b> <b><u>Yourself. The Big Six formed a convention in this country, blaming \"Crazy Creasy\" for</u></b> <b><u>riots. Joseph (+)</u> Ankrah led this country, which was also governed by Flight Lieutenant Jerry Rawlings. Kwame Nkrumah led this nation, formerly called (*) </b>Gold Coast, which was once dominated by the Ashanti. For the point, name this former British colony along the Volta River of West Africa.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Ghana</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This country's unification included the Battle of Kirtipur. The Rana Dynasty</u></b> <b><u>ruled this country after the Shah Dynasty, and this country faced the Jana Andolan</u></b> <b><u>movement under the United Left Front. In 2001, the crown prince (+)</u> Dipendra killed nine members of this country's royal family, including King Birendra. This country provides (*) </b>Gurkha soldiers and, up until 2008, it was the world's last Hindu monarchy. For the point, name this Himalayan republic that historically served as a buffer state between Imperial China and British India.", "answer": "Federal Democratic Republic of <b><u>Nepal</u></b> (accept Sa\u1e45gh\u012bya Lokt\u0101ntrik Ga\u1e47atantra <b><u>Nep\u0101l</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Minamoto no Yurimasa was the first known man to conduct this action, which</u></b> <b><u>later involved an individual known as a</u> </b><em><b><u>kaishakunin</u></b></em><b><u> who served as a (*)</u> \u201csecond.\u201d Hojo Ujimasa was once asked to undergo this action, which could involve a </b><em><b>tachi</b></em><b> or a shorter </b><em><b>tanto</b></em><b>. A favorite meal and white robes were often given before this action, which was sometimes referred to as (*) </b><em>hara-kiri</em>. The \u201cshadow belly\u201d was a fictional form of one type of this procedure often involving cutting the stomach. For the point, name this Japanese ritual suicide.", "answer": "<b><u>Seppuku</u></b> (accept <em><b><u>hara-kiri</u></b></em> before mentioned; prompt on ritual \u201csuicide\u201d or descriptive answers)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b><u>This leader launched three battles in the \"Strike Hard\" Anti-Crime Campaign.</u></b> <b><u>This person was placed under arrest in the April 5th, 1976 Tiananmen Incident. This</u></b> <b><u>man promoted science in the 863 plan, inspired by the U.S. Star Wars program. In a</u></b> <b><u>1992 (+)</u> Southern Tour, this man instigated the \"Reforms and Openness\" movement in Guangdong Province, creating a (*) </b>capitalist market. This leader ousted the Gang of Four and worked with the Eight Elders. For the point, name this Chinese leader whose market-economy reforms turned China into a modern state.", "answer": "<b><u>Deng</u></b> Xiaoping (prompt on \"Xiaoping\"; accept <b><u>Xixian</u></b>; accept <b><u>Teng</u></b> Hsiao-ping)", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}